Norman and Jeanne MacKenzie Papers, 1935-1964
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Norman Ian and Jeanne MacKenzie papers
1935-1964
MacKenzie, Norman Ian and Jeanne
99
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor, political and social science; Author. Papers document the work of Norman Ian MacKenzie in preparation for his report for the Social Science Research Council of Australia on the role and status of the Australian women, published as Women in Australia (1962). There is a small amount of material related to other publications written with wife and co-author, Jeanne MacKenzie.
Biographical Note
Norman Ian MacKenzie was born in London in on August 18, 1921. He graduated from the London School of Economics in 1943 (interrupted by war service in the Royal Air Force) with a B.Sc. (Economics). He was Assistant Editor of the New Statesman from 1943 to 1962. He taught at the University of Sussex, England from 1962 to 1983, initially as Lecturer in Sociology, retiring as Professor of Education. He edited The Letters of Sidney and Beatrice Webb (3 vols, 1978), as well as editing and writing books on various other subjects. Norman was commissioned by the Social Science Research Council of Australia to conduct a pioneering survey of the status and social and political roles of women in Australia in 1959-60, published as Women in Australia (1962). A revised edition was published as Women and Society: An Australian Study (with Sol Encel and Margaret Tebbutt) in 1975. He was awarded an Honorary Doctorate (D.Univ) by the Open University (1977) was an Honorary Fellow of LSE.
Daisy Jeanne MacKenzie née Sampson (but always known as Jeanne, pronounced Jean) was born in St. Helens, Lancashire, on January 30, 1922. She graduated from the London School of Economics in 1943 with a B.Sc. (Econ). She worked as a civil servant during World War II and subsequently as a reader for Hamish Hamilton (publishers) and as a marriage counselor. She wrote Australian Paradox (1961), A Victorian Courtship: The Story of Beatrice Potter and Sidney Webb (1979) and The Children of The Souls: A Tragedy of the First World War (1986); and edited a literary anthology, Cycling (1981).
Norman and Jeanne married 25 October 1945. The couple had two daughters, Janetta (1951-99) and Julia (b. 1956). They co-authored An Authentic and Faithful History of the Mysterious Murder of Maria Marten (1948); biographies of H. G. Wells (The Time Traveller: The Life of H. G. Wells, 1973; the early Fabians (The First Fabians, 1977); and Dickens: A Life (1979). They also co-edited The Diary of Beatrice Webb (4 vols., 1982-85). They were both made Fellow of the Royal Society of Literature and awarded the Society's Heinemann Prize for The First Fabians in 1978. After Jeanne's death in 1986, Norman married Dr. Gillian Ford in 1988. He died on June 18, 2013.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Norman and Jeanne MacKenzie Papers primarily document the work of Norman MacKenzie in preparation for his report for the Social Science Research Council of Australia on the role and status of the Australian women, published as Women in Australia (1962). The collection consists primarily of background research on the status of women in Australia and women's roles in education, labor and employment, family and home life, literature, politics, and the feminist and women's suffrage movements. Included are comparative studies for New Zealand, England, and the United States. There is also some material on Vida Goldstein, pioneer Australian suffragist; and Amy Johnson, the first woman to fly solo from London to Australia. Types of material include correspondence, typed and handwritten notes, original typed and handwritten manuscripts, surveys, reports, maps, reviews, pamphlets, clippings, memorabilia, and books. There is a small amount of material related to other publications written by Norman and co-author, Jeanne MacKenzie.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Norman and Jeanne MacKenzie donated their papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1965.
Goldstein, Vida, 1869-1949; Johnson, Amy, 1903-1941; Women--Australia--Social conditions--20th century-Sources; Women-Suffrage--Australia; Women's rights--Australia--History--20th century-Sources; MacKenzie, Jeanne; MacKenzie, Norman Ian. Women in Australia (1962)--Sources
Additional papers of Norman MacKenzie are at The Women's Library in London, England.
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bibliography 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Australian Paradox by Jeanne MacKenzie: correspondence and reviews 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photograph: Norman and Jeanne MacKenzie in Australia [copy print made from digital scan]circa 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 4b)
- Correspondence
  - Jeanne MacKenzie 1961-63 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norman Ian MacKenzie 1961-64 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Education: reports 1955-58 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Employment: reports 1935-60 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Equal pay: reports 1946-58 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Vida Goldstein, Australian Suffragette" (article) by Norman Mackenzie 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Home and family 1945-59 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lonely Moth: Amy Johnson's Flight to Australia by Norman MacKenzie n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Notes 1951-60 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous: address book, clippings, and reports 1944-60 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Politics and suffrage 1952-55 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Pamphlets 1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Women In Australia
  - Reviews, correspondence, and clippings 1961-63 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Introduction and chapters 1, 2 & 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Published book (1962) (Box 1)
  - Research materials
    - Role of women in public and professional Life 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Feminism: survey 1950-57 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Biographies of Australian women 1950-58 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Employment: war work 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous reports and statistics 1946-61 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Permissions 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Questionnaires n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Women's rights charters 1943-60 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Maps of Australia n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)